<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An inuitation vnto prayer, and the practise of piety, directing the way to true happinesse Wherein is principally to be considered, these foure things. 1. What prayer vnto God is. 2. The necessity of it. 3. The profit we receiue by this holy exercise. 4. The maner and vse of it.</title>
            <author>Perrott, James, Sir, 1571-1637.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09491</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19774</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100356</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836199</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836199</idno>
            <idno type="VID">455</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09491)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 455)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1526:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An inuitation vnto prayer, and the practise of piety, directing the way to true happinesse Wherein is principally to be considered, these foure things. 1. What prayer vnto God is. 2. The necessity of it. 3. The profit we receiue by this holy exercise. 4. The maner and vse of it.</title>
                  <author>Perrott, James, Sir, 1571-1637.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 129 [i.e. 127], [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Isaac Jaggard for Robert Bird, and are to bee sold at his shop in Cheapside, at the signe of the Bible,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Sir James Perrott.</note>
                  <note>Dedication signed: I.P. Knight.</note>
                  <note>A1 blank except for signature; page 118 misnumbered 120; 120-21 missing in number only.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 19324.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Identifed as STC 19324 on UMI microfilm.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:455:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:455:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:455:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:455:2"/>
            <p>AN Inuitation vnto Prayer, and the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of Piety, dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the way to true Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein is principally to</hi> be conſidered, theſe foure things.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>What Prayer vnto God is.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>The neceſſity of it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>The profit we receiue by this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>The manner and vſe of it.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> 
            </p>
            <p>London printed by <hi>Iſaac Iaggard</hi> for Robert Bird, and are to bee ſold at his ſhop in Cheapſide, at the ſigne of the Bible, 1624.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:455:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:455:3"/>
            <head>To my Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Worthy Friends in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL good counſell comes from God. Humane conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations are as fraile; as themſelues are feeble. Nature hath her cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and corruptions in all the accidents of this world. Mans aduice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng onely on it ſelfe, is
<pb facs="tcp:455:4"/> like his actions, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times prosperous, often perillous, &amp; many times pernitious. The moſt ſure and ſaſe helpe that vvee haue, comes from the gouernour of Heauen &amp; Earth. The defence of his truth is our beſt buckler, and his ſeruice our chiefeſt ſafety. Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Petitions vnto God, are the Harbin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, which prepares a place for our heauenly habitation, and makes firme our earthly poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. This ſmall and
<pb facs="tcp:455:4"/> ſlender Treatiſe, which J haue now puhliſhed concerning Prayer, was firſt written ahout <hi>27.</hi> yeares ſince, then penned for mine owne practiſe: ſince which time, it hath beene concealed, and in a manner caſt away, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst many my other looſe Papers, vntill of late finding it vnlooked for, J ſhewed it to ſome of my priuate Friends, whoſe deſires vvere; it ſhould be made publicke. To that J yeelded, not for any worth J could
<pb facs="tcp:455:5"/> conceiue to bee in the worke, comming from one ſo weake, but to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy thoſe who J knew would beare with my faults. Of all our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the world is as it were the Theater, our ſelues the Actors; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſome play their partes with skill, others in ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, most with errors: the greater part are cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers, more ready to finde fault with others, then to ſearch into them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: whatſoeuer they are, or J am, J ſee my
<pb facs="tcp:455:5"/> ſelfe ſubiect to cenſure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This ſubiect is Prayer, the pathway to happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: the handling and carriage of rich Roabes by poore men, makes not the garments meane, but it may be more meanely valewed, it is that in at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre as in Phyſicke; the Materials of the one, and ingredients of Medicines in the other, beeing of themſelues good, yet not well by the workers ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged, compoſed, and mixed; makes their ſhew of leſſe eſteeme; and
<pb facs="tcp:455:6"/> indeede their ſubſtance of leſſe vſe. Such may be the ſtate of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe touching prayers, the ſubiect in it ſelfe holy &amp; heauenly; but by mee not well handled; may ſo fall out to be leſſe valewed, then the dignity of it wel ſet forth, would ſhew it ſelfe to be. Howſoeuer, I offer this ſmall Widowes Myte into that Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie where true Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans by Prayer and Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, makes their oblations and tribute in the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary of GOD, vnto
<pb facs="tcp:455:6"/> whoſe gracious and good guidance, I commend all your good conſultations, with all others that by faithfull prayer and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent deuotion, deſire to ſerue his Diuine Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in him, who can make vs all his, and to enioy all happines.</hi> I. P. Knight.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:455:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:455:7"/>
            <head>
               <hi>AN INVITATION to Prayer, and the practiſe of Piety;</hi> dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the way to true Happineſſe. With a preparation to the practiſe thereof.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> What Prayer vnto God is.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore wee treate of this moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable gift and grace of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:455:8"/> Prayer; it is conuenient to know what Prayer
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. For of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s not knowne what they are, there is little deſire to attaine vnto them, be they neuer ſo excellent in them ſelues, or profitable vnto others. Therefore, to vſe a breefe definition, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſcription of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er vnto God: may be ſaid to bee, the Tribute of the ſoule, powring out praiſes vnto him for benefites al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready receiued, or making ſupplications for ſuch things as we ſtand in need of, and ſeeke of his Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Maieſty. Farther to make a celeſtiall repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, by terreſtrial com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon.</p>
               <p>Prayer vnto God, may
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:455:8"/> be termed to be as it were, a Bucket, to draw vp the water of Life, from the bottomles Well of Gods infinite grace and mercie. In the efficacie and effects it may bee likened vnto a ſtrong Wall or Fortreſſe, to guard the ſoule of him that rightly vſeth it, from the temptation and ſpoile of Sathan. So is it an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour againſt all aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and the Soules Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine againſt al maladies that doth inuade &amp; indan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger it. To conclude this, which brings vs to happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with that, which in Diuine contemplation of heauenly Myſteries, wee may ſomwhat ſhew what Prayer is, as the Diuines doe declare what God is,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:455:9"/> by ſignifying what hee is not, nor cannot be: So it may be ſaid of Prayer (a principall part of Gods worſhippe) not to be the ſport or ſupine exerciſe of humane Wit; nor the practiſe of ſloathfull crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures continuing in known ſinnes vnrepented; but it is an ardent and zealous inuocation, and (in ſome ſort) a Conference with God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Two partes of Prayer.</note>There are two parts of Prayer, as hath bin alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in part pointed out. For by ſhewing what Prayer is, we ſhew (in ſome ſort) of what it conſiſteth, that is; Petition, and Praiſe or Thankeſgiuing vnto God. Petition, is an humble ſuit and ſeeking vnto God, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:455:9"/> for pardon of our ſinnes, for ſupply of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall graces, or of tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall neceſſities, ſuch as our wants in both (which are great) doe vrge vs to aske for aſſiſtance from the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty. Praiſe &amp; Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, is an ardent and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty acknowledgment, with a landing of Gods moſt glorious name, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</p>
               <p>As there are two parts,<note place="margin">Two kinds of Prayer.</note> ſo there are two kindes of Prayer: the one, Mentall; the other, Vocall. The Mentall prayer is, vvhen our inward conceptions and meditations of the minde, are fixed on the Maieſty of God, by ſecret and ſilent recounting, (without expreſſion of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:455:10"/> words) the miſeries that our ſinnes haue brought vpon our ſelues: alſo, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we remember and reioyce at the mercies of God, and ſo do internally magnifie him for the ſame, and for his wonderfull workes of Iuſtice, iudgement, proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and preſeruation, without vttering of any words.</p>
               <p>The other kinde of Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Prayer, is, when the heart cannot be contained and ſatisfied onely vvith contemplation, but ſtriues to ſet the tongue &amp; voyce on worke, either priuately alone, or publikely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned with congregation and aſſembly of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, to pray vnto God, &amp; to praiſe him. The firſt is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:455:10"/> profitable, if it bee done with zeale, deuotion, and vnderſtanding: but the ſecond is commonly more firme and fruitefull<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For, when the ſoule is ſoliciting on this ſeruice of God, yet the exteriour ſences doe many times ſeduce and withdraw the inward me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ditation, which maketh them vaniſh, &amp; often wax vaine, except they be vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and bound together with the organs of voyce and ſpeech<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring make an euen har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony:<note place="margin">A compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> that inward as the Heart, which being the ſeate of the vitall ſpirites, g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ines quickning ſpirit to the body; this outward, being as the Lungs which receyued from within, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:455:11"/> vents outbreath<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> without which the heart it ſelfe cannot long continue in health; nor the body in life: So are they indeede both (whileſt they haue their well-being) like vnto <hi>Hippocrates</hi> twinnes born, bred, liuing and dying to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
               <p>It is true, that at al times they cannot be conioined; for ſometimes, Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation and Meditation may come, and are inuited into the heart by the good Spirite of GOD, at ſuch times and places; where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> publike nor pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> when ſtrength and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>acul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ech
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aileth,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> when th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:455:11"/> by contemplation may conſider, and ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſſe the frailties &amp; falles which are then, or hath bene before by them committed; and yet there is no opportunitie or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance to expreſſe it: there mentall Prayer and Meditation is moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. But vocall is moſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull, when it may bee practiſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. II.</hi> The Neceſsity of Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ext, to the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and knowledg what Prayer is, there comes to bee conſidered, what the neceſſitie is of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:455:12"/> ſame: wherein I might well conceyue, there ſhold neede no great labour to proue it; nor more then to prooue it, is day-light when the Sun ſhines: the one being manifeſt in the workes of Nature; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as apparant in the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Grace. Yet becauſe ignorance needs informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; curioſity requires confirmation, we will ſay ſomewhat, to make the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of prayer to bee in our ſight (as indeede it is in it ſelfe) perſpicuous and plaine.</p>
               <p>It is euident to all good and well inſtructed Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: That as wee are all Creatures of the heauenly Creator;<note place="margin">1. Prayer is needfull in reſpect of Creation.</note> ſo to this end, did he cheefely create vs;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:455:12"/> that we being his Worke-manſhip, we ſhould wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip our great Worke-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and giue him his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued glory, by acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging this innumerable benefites: in magnifying his Diuine Maieſty, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſupplications vnto him. Which moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſary Chriſtian dutie, wee cannot performe without Prayer. Therefore the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Prayer, is proued in the cauſe and end of our Creation.</p>
               <p>Next, as we are created onely by God;<note place="margin">2. For our Saluation.</note> ſo are wee onely ſaued by him: and of our ſelues, through our ſinnes Originall and Actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, we deſerue nothing but deſtruction, death, &amp; dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Therefore, as we
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:455:13"/> ſtand in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of pardon for our ſins, and of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pacifie Gods indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the ſinne, whome vnto doe dayly and gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly offend ſo can bee no way ſo well ſatisfie him, obtaine pardon of them, and ſaluation of our ſoules, as
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y frequent, zeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and feruent Prayer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the beſt procurers of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for our tranſgreſſions againſt God.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, as well our temporall preſeruation, as our Creation and Saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſheweth the neceſſitie of Prayer. For our youth is accompanyed with raſhneſſe; our riper yeares with dangerous aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: our elder yeeres, with ſickeneſſe and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:455:13"/> infirmities. In all which ſeaſons of mans life he is ſo ſubiect, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet with calamities, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and maladies both of minde, and of body, that without faithfull and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent Prayer vnto God, he cannot eſcape thoſe miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries where-with this life, and euery part thereof, is enuironed. And by accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Prayer vnto GOD he paſſeth thorow all theſe perils.</p>
               <p>Therefore, if wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider who is our Creator, what benefites hee hath beſtowed on vs, and to what end hee hath done this. In acknowledging, that hee hath created vs, we are bound to confeſſe his power &amp; prouidence.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:455:14"/> In beholding &amp; thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiuing his bleſſings, as life, helth, liberty, peace, wealth, knowledge, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, mutuall and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable ſociety, wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in duty but agnize his wonderfull bountie, cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, and mercy, which by no other meanes, be ſo performed, as by ardent &amp; deuout Prayer vnto God.</p>
               <p>So then we may ſee (if ſence do not blind reaſon, or if reaſon go not too far in giuing rules vnto Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion) the neceſſity of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er vnto God to be ſo great that without it we cannot well obtaine the things we rightly deſire, nor ſhun that which is hurtfull.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:455:14"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. III.</hi> Of the profit of prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He third thing to be conſidred, han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled, and well weighed, is the benefit and profit of praier vnto God, which though it cannot be truly valued by any but thoſe that feele the fruites of it; both inwardly in their comforts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and outwardly in their eſtates; and they on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that taſte and enioy the ſpiritual conſolation they feele and find in this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly exerciſe of prayer, can tell ſomewhat what it is: though they are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to expreſſe it, yet to ſhew ſome ſparkles of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:455:15"/> ſplendor of praier, (beſides that which hath beene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpoken of the nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of it) we will ſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily ſet downe, ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, what bene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ts the Children of God haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by the vſe of holy and faithfull prayer: and next touching the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which our Sauior hath made vnto ſuch as ſhall pray vnto God zealouſly and truly.</p>
               <p>If we looke into the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture and holy Bible; wee ſhall find ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient examples, of deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from dangers, &amp; the diuerting of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from ſinners, by the prayers of holy men, euen at the time, when moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent perils haue preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:455:15"/> themſelues.</p>
               <p>And when there hath beene no hope or likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of helpe to bee deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered by mortall man; yet the faithfull prayer of one man, hath deliuered many from deſtruction. As when the Iſraelites did fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Amalekites: as long as <hi>Aaron &amp; H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> held vp the hands of <hi>Moſes</hi> to pray, the Iſraelites did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile; when <hi>Iudas Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beus,</hi> fought againſt <hi>Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geas</hi> and his armie, againſt <hi>Lyſias</hi> and his armie; hee prayed; and by effectuall prayer vnto God, he ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came and got the victory. By prayer,
<hi>Moſes</hi> freed his Siſter from the Leproſie: and by prayer he pacified Gods diſpleaſure againſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:455:16"/> the people. And by praier, <hi>Abraham</hi> did oure <hi>Abime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech:</hi> all which, and many more examples, might be alledged, how profitable the praier of one man hath beene for the preſeruation of many.</p>
               <p>Then if we conſider the promiſes, which God (who is able to performe all that hee doth promiſe) hath made vnto all thoſe that make faithfull ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vnto him; wee ſhall finde the ſame to bee ſo great, as greater cannot come to man, by any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour. For it is ſaid, if two or three be aſſembled together to aske any thing lawfull in Gods name, hee will giue it.</p>
               <p>And againe, the holy
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:455:16"/> Ghoſt ſaith by the prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prophet <hi>David:</hi> Call vpon me in the time of thy need, and I will deliuer thee, and thou ſhalt praiſe me. Likewiſe the ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeaking by the ſame Spirit; Let him call vpon mee and I will heare him. I am with him in his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and will bring him to honour.</p>
               <p>But becauſe the ſacred Scriptures, are full of theſe certaine promiſes, for the obtaining of things faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and rightly asked of God in prayer, it ſhall bee ſufficient for confirmation of this point; to adde what our Sauiour himſelfe hath ſaid: Verily, verily, I ſay vnto you, whatſoeuer you ſhall aske for vnto the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:455:17"/> Father in my name it ſhall be giuen you.</p>
               <p>If then we be comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by God himſelfe, to pray vnto him, we cannot but clearly ſee, as in a Chriſtall glaſſe of Gods holy word, that prayer is moſt profitable for vs; as well for the fulfilling of Gods heauenly will, as for the accompliſhing of our owne godly deſires. And alſo, if wee ſee ſo many comfortable &amp; plaine pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternes of the great ſafety and ſaluation, that hath come, &amp; doth daily grow vnto the ſeruants of God, by hearty &amp; faithfull prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers vnto him: then haue we no cauſe to doubt the profit of prayer, or to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the doing of it, with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:455:17"/> our beſt deuotion.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, if wee looke into the plaine and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all promiſes of our All-po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull God, for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of that which we do effectually pray for; then there ſhal be no need of more perſwaſion of the ineſtimable benefit which powerfull prayer doth bring with it: neither ſhal there bee any neceſſity or motiue to follow &amp; fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the ſame, but willing minds, directed and aſſiſted by heauenly grace, to bee often conuerſant in this moſt holy and heauenly exerciſe of zealous prayer; which is ſo profitable vnto man, &amp; ſo acceptable and ſweet a ſacrifice vnto the Creator of mankind.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:455:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. IV.</hi> Of the manner of Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing as we hope ſhewed what prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is, and proued the neceſſity and profit thereof: next comes to be conſidered the manner of it, conſiſting in three things; that is, the time, place, and words, to bee vſed in prayer.</p>
               <p>Firſt, for the time of prayer, it ought not alwaies to bee limited, how often, or how long wee ſhould pray; but as often as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniently wee can, and as long as our faith without fainting, or time without diſtraction, will giue leaue. Neither are the preſcribed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:455:18"/> rules of the Romiſh Church, in this behalfe ſo profitable, or ſo tollerable, as to obſerue Mattin at ſuch houres, to ſay ſo many <hi>Creeds,</hi> ſo many
<hi>Aue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> ſo many <hi>Pater Noſters,</hi> and to recite the name of Ieſus, or the like, ſo many times, or to vſe ſuch and ſuch prayers, vppon ſuch Beades, vnto ſuch Saints, for ſuch men ſoules. As though God would haue mens deuotions practiſed more according to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of thoſe preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed rules and times, then at any other time, or in any other manner; or as if you were bound to heare them more in theſe regulated re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſals, then in any other ſort, when they ſhall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoted,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:455:19"/> to offer vp the ln<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe of Prayer &amp; Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing, being ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> therto, by the inwar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> good motion of zeale and deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which ought to be in vs at all times, as well as at any time certaine. But if the mind be not at al times well prepared to Prayer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yet as often as we may find time and meanes, we muſt endeuour to bee exerciſed therein, without ouer ſtri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t obſeruation of times limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; other then at ſuch times as we are called ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by a generall aſſembly of the Church and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation wherein we liue.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Likewiſe for the place of Prayer, it cannot be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes reſtrained nor ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:455:19"/> no more then the time can be alwayes limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. For although the Churche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (where the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the faithfull are or ought to bee aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled) bee the fitteſt place<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for Prayers, yet it ought not to be lonely there, but alſo elſewhere, becauſe men cannot be alwai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, or moſt commonly in the Church. And if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y may not bee there, yet euerie faithfull mans he attri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> time of prayer, is the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God. Whether ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee bee alone, or in company, or to what place ſoeuer he bee, his faithfull prayers ſhall be heard, and he is bound to pray: as Chriſt went alone in the Mountaine to pray, <hi>David</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:455:20"/> prayed in his houſe toppe, <hi>Ionas</hi> in the Whales belly,
<hi>Daniel</hi> in the Lyons den, <hi>Peter</hi> in the priſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the child
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pray in all places where they come, and as they ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, whether it bee in the Church, in the houſe, in the fields, in the war, and in time of peace, at home, and abroad.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Laſtly, for the words that ſhall be vſed in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, it is a matter worthy of conſideration, whith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they ought alwayes to bee ſet downe ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>taine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eyther in writing or in the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; before we come vnto prayer: Or whether they muſt be alwayes left vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> euery m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns meditation, &amp;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:455:20"/> preſent deliuery, as occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and his inuention ſhall ſerue him, or as the Spirit of God ſhall direct him: wherein, as they do affirm that prayers ought alwaies to be ſet downe in certaine words, may not haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of their opinions, ſo on the other ſide, ſuch as auerre, that the forme of prayer ſhold be at no time certaine, nor ſet downe in writing or in the memory, muſt not be beleeued, nor their aſſertions allowed as true and infallible.</p>
               <p>For the firſt ſort, which ſay, that one forme of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the ſelfeſame words, is alwayes to be vſed, they tye Gods guifts and grace<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (which are in euery man in ſome meaſure or other,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:455:21"/> ther more or leſſe) vnto preſcription, and to formal obſeruation, which moſt commonly begetteth cold affection in prayer. For, when a mans deuotion and all his meditation are tyed vnto certaine and vſuall words; there familiaritie of vttering one thing often taketh away the feeling of that which is vttered, ſo that it becommeth
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>it
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ip-labour; and loſeth the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent zeal of an inward de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, which doeth beſt pleaſe God in prayer; and without the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uency, prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is of none effect.</p>
               <p>Then touching their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions who affirme, that there ſhould bee no ſet forme of prayer at any time, or in any place, they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:455:21"/> do aſmuch erre, as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer (which follow tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and preſcription one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in prayer.) For in Churches, in Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and in Aſſemblyes, where publike Prayer is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and where manie doe frequent to pray together, there no doubt, that a form of prayer is very profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, both for vnity and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall framing of mens mindes and inward affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in one ſence, &amp; in one ſaying, and at one time, to lift vp both hands &amp; harts vnto God; which is the ſweeteſt harmony that can bee on earth. And more then that, it is the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly harmony, that tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth our bodies, our minds and our ſoules from earth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:455:22"/> vnto heauen. But as this vnity and ſetled forme of prayer is moſt profitable and needefull in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like aſſemblies; ſo in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate prayers and inuocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ought no man to bee forbidden the vſe of his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and ſeuerall Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, according as God ſhal giue him grace and abilitie to praiſe him, and to pray vnto him. For, although it be not euery mans guift, to deliuer in apt wordes, the ſecret and particular deſires of his ſoule in prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers vnto God: yet there is no doubt, but the man of meaneſt conceite and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, hauing a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to performe his duty in this ſeruice of God; ſhall finde (by exerciſe and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:455:22"/> heerein) his minde more apt, This ſences more ſharp, and his words more ready, with daily and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall vſe of prayer.</p>
               <p>Therefore, as euerie man ought not in publicke places of prayer, to follow his owne forme, and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate himſelfe in prayer from the Congregation; ſo in priuate prayer, no man ought to bee forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den that forme of prayer, which his faith and capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie can affoord, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſenſe and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of his ſinnes, the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of his ſoule, and the neceſſitie of his preſent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate.</p>
               <p>Next vnto the time, the place, and words for vs to vſe in prayers, there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:455:23"/> to bee conſidered, the Faith and feruencie, that ſhould accompany our prayers, with a moſt principall &amp; eſſentiall part thereof: this ought to be in feruency of ſpirit, without fainting<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for to pray with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out zeale, is but to tempt and mocke God. And God will not bee worſhipped in words onely, without y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward affection of the hart, which is as well knowne to God (the ſearcher of reines and heart) as the words that are vttered in prayer. Therefore they which pray without faith &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feruency, performe no more then plants which growe without feeling. Nay, they do not ſo much: for the one doth performe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:455:23"/> the workes of nature which it is not taught to doe, but the others do forſake, &amp; not follow the rules of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which by reaſon, and inſtruction they are infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and required to doe. It is not then ſufficient to ſay many prayers, and to continue long in prayer: for as one ſaith, the true ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of prayer conſiſteth not in bare words, nor in the multitude of wordes that wee ſpeake, but in the cogitations and faithfull deſires of the heart. And it is not our words, but our deſires that enters into the ſecret eares of the All-hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, Al-giuing, and Al-ſeeing God. How much then doe they wrong the Maieſty of God, and the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:455:24"/> ſaluation of their ſoules, which runne to prayers as vnto a ſtage play, without any preparation, without any Faith, or without any zeale, but heaping vp pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, &amp; yet ſcarce thinking what they ſay, or to whom they do pray.</p>
               <p>The Aſtronomers affirme, that the Moone is Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, when the earth is inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, betwixt her and the Sunne: ſo may it be auer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the meditations which we deliuer in praier, are much eclipſed and darkned, when earthly co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations doe interpoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the mind of man, &amp; his diuine Meditation, which is the Sun ſhine &amp; cleareſt light of his ſoule. Prayer vnto Gody, is i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:455:24"/> conferrence with God: therefore <hi>Auguſtine</hi> calleth the booke of his prayers and meditations, his <hi>Solilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quium,</hi> that is, the alone talke or ſecret conference of his ſoule with God. How carefull, zealous and humble then ought wee to be in our conferre with ſo great a Lord, and our onely God? For when any men doth conſerue with his better (eſpecially with one that is farre his ſuperiour) as a Nobleman, a Prince, or any great perſonage, how circumſpect will hee be to ſhewe all the ſignes of reuerence, and duty in word in geſture, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance; and if he doe not vſe all theſe obſeruations, which may teſtifie his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:455:25"/> and obeiſance vnto his ſuperiour, he may feare to bee noted of preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to incurre the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of him, with whom hee conferreth. If then ſuch ceremony and reuerence bee vſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in conference, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twxit man and man, how much more careful, watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and fearefull, ought e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man to bee in prayer, which is his conference with God. Therefore hee that will pray vnto God effectually, ought in the time of prayer, wholly to exerciſe his mind and his ſenſes in the conſtant, faithfull, deuout, and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent calling vpon his Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator, hauing mind on no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther matter, then on his
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:455:25"/> meditations which he doth preſent, nor on any other perſon then his God, to whom hee doth deliuer them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. V.</hi> A preparation to prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſomewhat the property of prayer to God, and what it is: the neceſſity, manner, and profit thereof, it will not be amiſſe, or vnneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to ſhew ſomething of the preparation that ſhould be made, before we do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into this holy exerciſe. For as before wee f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll into any actiuity of the body,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:455:26"/> exerciſe of the mind, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther action of accompt, (which wee deſire ſhould bee acceptable vnto them, before whom wee preſent the ſame) there is alwayes ſome time of preparation taken, to the end the ſame may be the more exquiſite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly managed: ſo is it much more needfull, that before this ſpirituall, exerciſe of prayer, a ſound preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the mind and ſoule ſhould ſtill be premiſed, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it may fall out in this holy exerciſe as it doth in matters of far loſſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that is not well prepared; may bee ſoone intrapped &amp; diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. The beſt rules there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that my ſimple iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can affoord for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:455:26"/> to prayer are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Firſt, before wee begin our prayers, we ſhould fall into ſome ſtrict examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſelues, touching our ſinne, and the eſtate of our life; wherein wee may beſt conſider, what we had moſt need to craue at Gods hands.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Next, we muſt call to remembance the mercies of God, his iuſtice, his iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and his wonderfull workes; whereby in our prayers we may learne, and vſe (aſwell as in the reſt of our life) to loue him for his mercies; to feare him for his iuſtice, and iudgements, aſwell as to magnifie him
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:455:27"/> for his wonderfull workes; which cogitations conioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, may make our follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing meditations more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and profitable.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Thirdly, before wee fall vnto prayer, wee ought to ſequeſter our ſenſes from all wandering, idle, &amp; vaine cogitations, and to caſt away all euill thoughts as <hi>Helias</hi> did caſt his Man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle to the earth, when he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended to heauen: reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing fully with the fauour of God (whom we purpoſe then to ſerue) not to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine any worldly thoghts that may with-drawe our deuotions from his diuine Maieſty, but to baniſh all paſſions, pleaſures, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations of the mind, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:455:27"/> to recall vnto memorie, our laſt and moſt preſſing ſins, by an inward feeling of them, ioyned with repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, &amp; a purpoſe to pray for pardon and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Then being thus chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anly reſolued, we muſt yet before wee begin to pray, labour to bring with vs by faith, a liuely and a longing apprehenſion of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and mercies: and an vndoubted beleefe of his moſt iuſt &amp; heauenly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of that which he hath graciouſly promiſed, and we doe faithfully pray for.</p>
               <p>Afterwards, when by meditation we haue made this paſſage for prayer,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:455:28"/> which requires faithfull &amp; watchfull progreſſe, if yet wee finde, as vſually wee may finde, that any euill or vaine thoughts doe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalt vs, when we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming on to this holy exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, we muſt ſeeke euen at the firſt feeling thereof, to reſiſt and reiect it, without giuing any kinde of ſmall entertainement thereto: conſidering, that euill co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations are of two kinds, either immitted or permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: they are immitted by the frailty of the fleſh, the temptations of Sathan, the weakneſſe of the inner ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, being deluded by the obiects which the exterior ſenſes (eſpecially the ſight) doth conuey vnto them: and theſe immitted euill
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:455:28"/> cogitations, doe hurt the heauenly Meditations of our prayers: eſpecially, when they are permitted to harbour and to remaine within vs. Therefore, as ſoone as any ſuch tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions come towards vs in our prayers, we muſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently pray vnto God, to ſtrengthen our Faith, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue our frailty, and aſſiſt vs with his holy Spirit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch temptations.</p>
               <p>Alſo, when wee begin, and after wee haue begun our prayers, we muſt bring with vs, and keepe with vs this conſideration and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, not to ſeeke ſo much temporall as ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all bleſſings at Gods hands. And if our neceſſities call vpon vs to craue temporal
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:455:29"/> bleſſings; yet let our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires be ſo farre limited, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to ſubmit our wills to Gods heauenly will: let vs begin to begge of God things ſpirituall, before temporal bleſſings, though both be neceſſary, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be neglected.</p>
               <p>To all this muſt bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Charity, in pardoning offences that are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt vs, according to the preſident &amp; precept which our Sauiour himſelf hath ſet downe in that forme of prayer, vvhich ought to be the rule of all our prayers; and ſo recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciling our ſelues firſt by charity to our aduerſaries, we may come with more cleere Conſciences, and more acceptable ſacrifice,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:455:29"/> in our ſupplications vnto God. For if wee aske for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of our ſins, and do not forgiue others, wee can find but little aſſurance to obtaine what we aske.</p>
               <p>So then we ſee, it is not fit nor ſafe, to runne raſhly vnto prayer, without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, premeditation, faith, repentance, recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, and reſiſtance of temptations.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. VI.</hi> An entrance to Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing prepared our mindes, and our heartes for Prayer, we may then moſt ſafely make our entrance into it, which conſiſteth
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:455:30"/> chiefely of theſe parts; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation, Confeſſion, La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or Thankeſgiuing, &amp; Supplication, Inuocation, is a calling or appellation on the name of God moſt high. Which declareth &amp; denounceth the attributes belonging to the nature of God, and theſe doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne his Iuſtice, Mercie, Power, &amp; his Prouidence. His Iuſtice, as a moſt iuſt God, who by thy Iuſtice doeſt diſtribute &amp; diſpoſe vnto all creatures, all that belongs, and is moſt fitte for them; who therby doſt gouerne and guide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and men, with all that is in heauen and earth.</p>
               <p>His Mercy, as thus: Moſt mercifull and gracious God, whoſe mercy is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:455:30"/> all thy other won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull workes, in pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and preſeruing from deſtruction, and in ſending thy Son to ſaue ſinners.</p>
               <p>The inuocation of Gods Power, may bee made af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner. O God, of vnſpeakeable power and might, which madeſt all things of nothing by thine owne onely word &amp; wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and art able at all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing all this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vnto nothing.</p>
               <p>The inuocation of Gods prouidence, may be in this wiſe. O Lord God of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful wiſedom, he whoſe prouidence all things are preſerued, and from whoſe wiſedome we haue all our knowledge and wiſedom. Theſe and the like inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:455:31"/> according to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation and declaration of Gods attributes uttered in this or the like ſort, may ſerue as ſome inſtruction to the ignorant: ſo from Introduction and entrance into their prayer, vntill by practice they bee made more perfect, as the firſt part thereof, yet to be alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, amended, &amp; augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as euery mans capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ability ſhall affoord him meanes.</p>
               <p>Next to Inuocation in prayer, Confeſſion hath her proper place. For if we haue offended God (as there is no man but dayly and hourely doth it: then it is moſt needfull,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> firſt we do confeſſe our ſelues, before we ask any benifits.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:455:31"/>This Confeſſion is of two kindes, the one, gene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rall; the other, particular. That generall, as when one doth declare and deplore his greeuous ſinnes, that hee is polluted with the ſame thoroughout all his parts and faculties: the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which is a mention and recitall of ſeuerall ſinnes, ſuch as euery man may finde himſelfe to bee moſt burdened with; as thoſe which were laſt commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, moſt freſh in memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; namely, that this day, &amp; of late I haue done theſe euils in thy ſight: I haue ſeduced ſuch perſonnes, I haue ſlandered my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; I haue in this deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or darkened the truth; I haue harbored theſe euil
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:455:32"/> thoughts of ſuch perſons, without iuſt cauſe giuen; I haue followed this vaine deſire, affected this fond inuention preſented to me by others, or entertayned by my ſelfe; I haue not withſtood ſuch an euill worke, when I could haue done it; I haue bene ſilent in ſuch a cauſe, when I might haue made the truth manifeſt. And ſo of our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall ſinnes either com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, whereof wee may take knowledge; or of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary duties omitted, which in Chriſtian dutie wee ought to haue done, when wee make faithfull confeſſion vnto God, ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with ſome repentance, and the ſame accompanied with acknowledgement &amp;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:455:32"/> Thankſgiuing for mercies receiued, are the beſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratiues in our prayers.</p>
               <p>After this, and the like, both generall and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar confeſſions of our ſins in prayer vnto God; a lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and a thankeſgiuing for the bleſſings imparted vnto vs (wherof we ought to be ſenſible, and not to be ſilent) comes next in place. For it were vnſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, inconuenient, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouident, to ask any new good turnes of any man, before we return any ſhew of thankefulneſſe for what good we haue receiued: ſo would it bee as vnbeſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and altogether as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, for mortall man to pray vnto the immortal God, for any encreaſe of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:455:33"/> mercies; before hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge thoſe which haue beene formerly pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on him. The forme of this praiſe and thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing may bee made after this manner. We praiſe and magnifie thy Diuine Maieſty, moſt glorious God, for thy fauour and goodneſſe extended al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes on vs ſinfull Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſince our Creation, for giuing vs vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thee, and of thy wil; for preſeruing, maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and protecting vs more particularly for &amp;c. Laſtly, ſupplication, or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition is to be made (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for the pardoning of our ſinnes, for freeing and keeping vs from fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into the ſame, or the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:455:33"/> like againe, for the obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſpirituall graces, and of temporall neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for the pardoning of ſinnes, it may bee in ſuch like ſort: Thou that art the God of mercy, ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and compaſſion on me a moſt miſerable ſinner: Lord let thy mercie ſhine aboue all thy other works. Caſt not thy louing coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance from me, beway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling my many &amp; heynous tranſgreſſions. Lord God, thou ſeeſt our wantes and our weakeneſſe. I beſeech thee ſtrengthen me in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and in health. Bleſſe me in eſtate, that I may be the better able to ſerue thee, and imploy what thou ſhalt affoord, according to thy ſacred will &amp; pleaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:455:34"/>The ſupplication for ſpirituall graces may be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this wiſe: Though wee haue deſerued no goodnes hauing done ſo much euill; yet according to thy won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted goodnes, grant vs ſuch graces and heauenly gifts, as may make vs bleſſed in thy ſight, and beloued of thy Saints Giue me a ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt faith, an humble &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite heart, penitence for all my ſinnes paſt, watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe ouer my waies for time to come, zeale of thine honour and glory, a loue of thy truth, and of ſuch as loue the ſame, an vnderſtanding heart to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne it, conſtancie in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing and keeping thy commandements: teach me to examine mine owne
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:455:34"/> heart, to ſearch it ſtrictly, to ſee if there yet remaine any hypocirſie or hollow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in it: Take from mee the temptations of luſt, vaine-glory, malice, ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ality, diſtruſt &amp; diffidence of thy power or mercy, that ſo through thy onely and all-able aſſiſtance, I may bee made of a ſinfull ſoule, though not a perfect, yet an acceptable worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, of thee my Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord, and onely Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="admonitions">
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:455:35"/>
            <head>Short Admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerning the premiſes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall deſire the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable viewer of theſe imperfect rules concerning prayer, to conceiue that they are not ſet downe either to informe the learned, or any that are well exerciſed in prayer. But to giue ſome light vnto ſuch as are young, ſimple, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, or not much vſed to prayer.</p>
            <p>Neither ſhould any of them bee tied onely to theſe words or formes heere ſet downe, but it is in their choiſe to take the ſence of the ſame, ſo farre as they ſhall finde it
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:455:35"/> to further their good and godly indeauours in prayer. And if GOD ſhall indue them with better abilities, they may vſe them, ought to be thankfull for that heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly talent they haue, and not to hide or to abuſe it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:455:36"/>
            <head>A prayer for deuotion in prayer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ince all good gifts comes from thee, our gracious God, the author of all goodnes: grant vs thy ſpeciall ſauing grace of ſanctified &amp; fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent prayer, in frequent and zealous ſupplications. Wee haue it not of our ſelues, we ſeeke it of thee: nether can wee ſeeke it, without thou firſt ſend the motions thereof into our hearts and mindes: prepare vs therefore for this holy duty, grant vs the practice and power of it before we come to it; touch our hearts with the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of our ſinnes, and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:455:36"/> repentance for the ſame. Call to our memorie and meditations, how ſlowe wee haue beene to preſent our ſelues to thy preſence by prayer, how cold wee are in deuotion, how di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted in our thoughts, and how full of fantaſies, and of fond imaginations, which draw our zeale and deuotion from thee, even in the time of praier, when our thoughts ſhould bee pure, and our hearts onely ſetled vpon thy ſeruice: ſo that in ſtead of bringing a bleſſing, we bring iuſt cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to our ſelues, by theſe our more formall then faithfull praiers. O Lord, therefore infuſe grace in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our hearts, kindle zeale, fortifie our faith, let not
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:455:37"/> our ſecure and ſenſuall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of thee, increaſe more of our abounding ſinnes, nor adde more to thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued anger; but be thou in the middeſt of vs, by thy aſſiſting holy Spirit. When wee lift vp our hands, lift thou vppe our hearts vnto thee: when we ſpeake vnto thee, ſpeake thou peace vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Conſciences: giue vs words to vtter, faith to beleeue, feruencie in our prayers, an earneſt deſire to abandon all euil affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and looſe carriage of our cogitations, and ſo cloſely to ſettle our ſoules vnto thy ſeruice. When we come to make our ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications before thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, let this inſtant time of prayer, whileſt we now
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:455:37"/> ſpeake, bee the beginning of our better ſeruice, and ſo continuing in the ſame, with humility, conſtancy, and fauour; thou maieſt haue the honour, and wee the benefit. To thee bee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen all honour and glory, now and all times, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="family, morning" type="prayer">
            <head>Morning prayer in a familie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God, light of lights, thou that giueſt light vnto our ſoules, and to our bodies; thou that haſt brought vs from the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this night, to ſee the comfortable light of this day; bring vs from the darkneſſe of ignorance
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:455:38"/> and of ſinne, and from the corrupting of our ſoules, wherein wee haue liued both day and night. As thou haſt raiſed vs from our reſts to follow our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings; ſo raiſe vs from ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſloath, dulneſſe, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction, luſt, couetouſnes, ſelfe-conceites, pride, and all other corrupt affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which carry vs head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long after the vaine imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of our owne harts, and euill affections. Good Lord, when we go abroad about our worldly affaires, let not our mindes bee led altogether from heauenly meditations: but let thy bleſſed Spirit be our moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner, to put vs in minde of the ſhortneſſe and vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of our liues, let vs
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:455:38"/> haue before our thoughts often, the ſinnes wee haue committed, the good wee might haue done, and haue omitted; the time wee haue miſpent, either in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no good at all, or in doing that is euill. And this (good Lord) teach vs to tell our ſelues, and our owne ſoules, not with wordes, onely comming from the lippes, but with inward ſighs and groanes from the heart: and when through the aſſiſtance of thy holy Spirit thou haſt made vs to ſearch our ſins, and to ſmite our hearts, then bleſſe thou the works of our hands in all our good endeauours: and as by the ſame our ſtore doth encreaſe, our thankfulnes
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:455:39"/> to thee may encreaſe: As thy bleſſings are beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo our prayers &amp; prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes may bee rendred and redoubled. At our going out, in our reſt, trauaile, and returne, bee thou with vs, by the bleſſing and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of thy holy Spirit; let this day (good Lord) bee a beginning and a new birth day of faith, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for our ſinnes, and of reconciliation to thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty; that ſo thou mayeſt receiue vs to mercy. Let al the reſt of our dayes be an amendment of our ſinfull liues paſt. Bleſſe (good Lord) thy Church, our King, &amp; his Realmes, with faith, truth, peace, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie; guide the reſt of the States of this land in
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:455:39"/> their ſeuerall conditions &amp; callings; that both they and we may maintaine thy truth, ſet forth thy glory, keepe a good conſcience to our ſelues, &amp; ſhew cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity one vnto another. So wee may liue in thy feare, dye in thy fauour, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this mortall life is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, we may enioy an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall life with thee in heauen, there to magnifie, praiſe, and glorifie thy moſt glorious Name, world without end, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="private, morning" type="prayer">
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:455:40"/>
            <head>A Morning Prayer to be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in priuate.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His day (our good God) appearing, and thy mercies appearing by our deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from dangers this night paſt, and in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining of dayes, and of all thy other workes: what praiſes ſhall we render for thy workes of Creation, and of preſeruation? If we ſhould not praiſe thee, yet one day telleth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and one night certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth another; but I moſt ſinnefull ſoule, haue ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther expreſſed, nor felte what belongs to the viſible workes of thy inuiſible Maieſty; neither can I
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:455:40"/> comprehend it in thy workes, and made known by thy reuealed word: for thy Maieſty is ſo great, thy Wiſedom ſo vnſerch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and thy Word ſo deepe, that I am not able to conceiue them. It ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeth (great God) vnto thee that art al-ſufficient in thy ſelfe, to expreſſe thy ſelf vnto vs ſinners, in ſuch ſort as we are able to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend thee. And I, one of the leaſt and vnworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſeruants, doe confeſſe my ſelfe to be a moſt gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous ſinner, in thought, word, and deede: I haue followed mine owne wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked fantaſies, I haue bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken thy commandements, and betrayed mine owne ſoule; yet my hope is in
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:455:41"/> thy mercie: and therefore in the beginning of this day, I beginne my prayers vnto thee; teach me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to pray, that I may this day, and the reſt of my life, call vpon thee, and praiſe thee through the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of thy power, which graunt vs good Lord.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="family, evening" type="prayer">
            <head>A Prayer for the Euening in the Family.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt gracious God we thanke thee for our ſafe deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance this day, &amp; the reſt of our life from all daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. That thou haſt giuen vs food, health, rayment, with other things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for our ſuſtenance and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:455:41"/> ſuſtentation. That thou haſt not ſuffered vs to bee ouerwhelmed with cares, croſſes, and calamities, whereto wee are ſubiect, whilſt we lead this tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory life. That thou haſt granted vs liberty to trauel in thoſe affaires, to which our eſtates and neceſſities do call vs. Theſe, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other bleſſings, haſt thou beſtowed on vs this day, and from day to day vntill this preſent time. O Lord, as thou haſt powred downe thy mercies vppon vs in great meaſure, ſo ſhowre downe into our hearts thoſe thy heauenly graces of thankefulneſſe, faithfulneſſe, fauour, and praiſes, that they may bee like vnto Dewe comming
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:455:42"/> downe from Heauen; which aſcending vp thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againe, and ſo retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thence with retribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of encreaſe, may moi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten our dry, hard, &amp; ſtony hearts, and ſo bring forth fruits of Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which may grow vp to the ſetting forth of thy glory, and the ſauing of our owne poore ſinnefull ſoules.</p>
            <p>To this end good Lord, ſettle our hearts this Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning before, and when we go to bed; as we cary with vs our corruptions, ſtill plucking vnto our fraile bodies fleſh and blood; ſo yet with the aſſiſtance and ſtrength by which we muſt walke, or elſe wee can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſtand, we may bee led
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:455:42"/> to the conſideration of our owne mortality &amp; miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble condition, that we are now aliue, and may die ere the next day; that though we haue fedde plentifully this day, yet it may be we ſhall eate no more; &amp; that ſome of vs who heare and ſee one another now, ſhall neuer heare or ſee one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other hereafter. For ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of vs haue aſſurance to liue vntill the next day, to deliuer what wee haue done this night. Bleſſed God therfore, we beſeech thee, euen at this inſtant time, begin to infuſe grace into vs, to looke vpon our ſelues as corruptible, and to looke into our ſoules as they are ful of corruption, to make a true account at
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:455:43"/> the leaſt, of this daies treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, committed againſt thy holy &amp; heauenly Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, to mourne for it as much as we may, before ſleepe the fore-ſhewer of death doth ſeize vpon vs, to pray vnto thee feruent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to aske thee forgiuenes; to giue thee thanks for thy mercies, to lift vppe our hands and harts vnto thee, and at the leaſt to ſay, Lord be mercifull vnto me a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſinner. This repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and this continuall practice of prayer, of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and of thankeſgiuing, grant vs good Lord, and to all thy choſen children, for thy Sonne our Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus ſake.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="private, evening" type="prayer">
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:455:43"/>
            <head>A priuate Prayer for one go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to bed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His day (good Lord) is ſpent; ſo doe our liues ſpend: &amp; as our time doth decreaſe, ſo do our ſinnes encreaſe. We ſeeke riches and know not who ſhall enioy them: Wee couet children, wealth, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments, and are not aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to poſſeſſe them. And I that ſhould know thus much, doe not conſider what I know, nor weigh mine owne infirmities. I haue (good Lord) this day acted my part, with much frailty, and many faylings. I haue forgotten to call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon thee my Soueraigne
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:455:44"/> Lord) this day, and moſt of the dayes of my life: my faith is weake, my vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is dull in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine things, my memorie failes to retayne good things, though they bee taught me, my affections depriued and wandering after vaine, worldly, and wicked imaginations, the which carry mee from the keeping of thy Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements. This (O Lord) I confeſſe, and better I am not able to do without thy aſſiſtance: yet keepe mee (gracious God) this night, and from henceforth, from further contagion of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and of ſoule; let not my polutions in the works of darkeneſſe this night, be added to my former tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:455:44"/> but cleanſe mee from that is paſt, and keep me from the like ſins from time to time; change the Old man in me by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and renouation, ſaue my ſoule, and teach me to ſet forth thy praiſe, both day and night.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="evening" type="meditations">
            <head>Certaine Meditations, and ſhort eiaculations of Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to bee vſed in the night.</head>
            <p>A Waking out of ſleepe, let vs begin with ſome ſhort prayers in this or the like ſort.</p>
            <p>My God, I am awaked againe: awake mee out of ſinne, as thou haſt done me out of ſleepe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:455:45"/>Let my ſleepe, wherein I had not the vſe of my ſenſes, teach mee not to driue out my daies in ſlumber, ſecurity, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety.</p>
            <p>When I ariſe out of my bed, raiſe me vp to new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life, repentaunce for my ſinnes, and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of what I haue done amiſſe.</p>
            <p>When mine eyes ſhall cloſe againe, keepe mee in thy protection &amp; ſafegard by thy power.</p>
            <p>Now Lord defend me this night, and euer; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue me from danger, ſin, and death.</p>
            <p>Keepe me from concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence, luſt, and vaine imaginations.</p>
            <p>Knit my hart vnto thee.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:455:45"/>Let my ſleep be mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and ſafe, ſo that I may riſe better prepared for thy ſeruice.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="deliverance" type="prayer">
            <head>A Prayer for deliuerance from temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>VR fraile Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and our proneneſſe to fall into all kind of ſins, forceth vs, O Lord, (if we would doe as wee ſhould) to flye vnto thee for our ſafety and ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to call vpon thee, who art our ſtay and our ſtrength, and who onely haſt power to preſerue vs: beſeeching thee, that thou wilt be pleaſed, either to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:455:46"/> put vs from thoſe tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which of our ſelues wee are not able to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. Teach vs O Lord, to wreſtle with ſinne and with Sathan by prayers &amp; reparations, framed and fitted by the inſpiration of thy holy Spirit: and when theſe temptations are offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, offer vnto vs thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping hand, to ſtand ſtedfaſt in faith, with feare to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thee. Let vs then, when theſe temptations come, ſay vnto our ſelues, Lord, thou ſeeſt all, and thou wilt puniſh vs; Lord help, and Lord deliuer vs, and for my ſinfull weake ſelfe, ſaue mee from theſe violent aſſaults of Sathan. I cannot defend my ſelfe, he thou therfore my ſhield
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:455:46"/> and buckler, my corrupt nature is ready to yeelde; the contagions of others, the allurements of the world, and wicked perſons are ready to enthrall me: yet if thou (my mercifull God) ſtrengthen me, I ſhall be able by thy aſſiſtance to ſtand; If thou (my Sauior) ſtretch out thy ſhield and ſpeare of defence, I ſhall with <hi>Peter</hi> (being almoſt ſunke) walke ſafe on the waters of ſtrife. Helpe therefore Lord, for vaine is the helpe of man. Put from vs Pride, Preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Luxury, Luſt, Selfe-conceite, Couetouſneſſe, want of deuotion, Malice, Miſchief, Vnbeleefe, hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, &amp; ſuch like ſinnes, which are the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:455:47"/> ſubiects of our temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: or if any ſuch aſſault vs, or come neere vs, let them not take ſuch holde on vs to throw vs downe, that we be not able to riſe any more; but in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, or before the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uailing of our temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſupport, deliuer, and ſaue vs. So ſhall we giue thee laud for euer and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="patience" type="prayer">
            <head>¶ A Prayer for patience, in time of wants and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graces.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is iuſt with thee (O Lord) and I haue iuſtly deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that thou ſhouldeſt ſend me ſome wants and ſmall diſgraces, after thou
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:455:47"/> haſt giuen me proſperitie, plenty, and ſufficiencie: when not vſing thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings well, and neglecting the meanes thou haſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorded for my maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, I am faln from that I had (which was ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent) to want ſome things for my neceſſary vſe. And yet my wants are not ſo great as my ſinnes are, or as they haue deſerued. Since then, howſoeuer my eſtate, or my eſtimation is in this world, I do beſeech thee graunt me patience to beare this, or whatſoeuer croſſe it pleaſeth thee to lay vpon mee, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that I my ſelfe am the cauſe of it. And ſo, when thou haſt brought me home vnto thy ſelf, by
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:455:48"/> the acknowledgement of my ſelfe, and of my ſinnes, comfort me againe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy eternall wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that I bee neyther diſmaide with aduerſitie, or puffed vp with proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: but if it be thy good pleaſure, that pouerty ſhall ſtill purſue mee; prepare me with patience to beare this croſſe, though hard for fleſh and blood: yet once obtaining the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie by thy ſole ſtrength, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer this inward enemy, &amp; my infirmities ſticking cloſeſt vnto me, I may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe my ſoul in peace: and whatſoeuer becomes of my worldly eſtate, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſtate of my ſoul may be ſafe, &amp; I ſaued, thorow thy abundant mercies, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="family, sickness" type="prayer">
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:455:48"/>
            <head>A Prayer in time of ſickneſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt gracious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we confeſſe and wee are dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to confeſſe, wee haue deſerued plagues, peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and other ſickneſſes whereto we are ſubiect of our ſelues, aſwell by the naturall infection of our bodies, whereby one ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth contagion from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as by our ſpirituall pollutions, whereby our ſinnes, being the inward feſtring ſores, doe aſcend vnto the Tribunall in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, calling and crying for vengeance on the earth, &amp; on the ſonnes of men, the inhabitants and Rulers of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:455:49"/> the earth. The effects of this (good Lord) we haue often and viſibly ſeene, though wee doe not well conſider the cauſe. Wee feele the ſtroke, but do not ſee the hand that ſtrikes; neither do we well weigh what moues that hand to bee ſtretched out agaynſt vs.</p>
            <p>Now the ſickneſſe thou haſt ſent vs, makes vs to looke ſomewhat about vs, and to feel that which our fleſh can eaſily find; paine, anguiſh, aches, &amp; torments comming from the body, to the mind. But (O Lord) we are not ſo ſenſible of that which concernes the ſickneſſe of the ſoule. Yet in this time of our viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whileſt paine and perill
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:455:49"/> doth oppreſſe vs, teach vs to take this as an informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our infirmities: heale vs (good Lord) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in the diſeaſes of our ſoules, and keepe vs from thoſe corruptions of our naturall affections, which draws vs vnto fond deſires, with falſe and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh appetites, the procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of theſe our bodily di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes.</p>
            <p>O Lord yet cleanſe vs within from our ſins, and then we ſhalbe cured from our corporall ſicknes; but if it be thy bleſſed will to continue this Contagion, yet comfort and ſupport vs during the time of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Make thou (good Lord) our beddes and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, ſuch as may make vs
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:455:50"/> able to vndergo our ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; comfort vs with the inward conſolation of thy holy Spirit, &amp; when cold, heat, coniunction, or ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of either comes, then O Lord, in the time of extremity, whileſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is diſtempred, our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſed, &amp; our minds diſtracted, betwixt feare of death, danger of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, care of our children, friends, kindr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, and fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, wee may y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t receyue a ſweet repoſe from the in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fluence of thy holy Spirit, to reſt content with thy good will and pleaſure; with a reference and rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the ſame, for reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of life, or of death. So may wee, by thy aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, ſay ſtill and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:455:50"/> vnto thee, in the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of our owne ſoules; We are heere now (good Lord) at thy diſpoſing, do with vs what thou wilt. Only make vs able to bear our owne infirmities, and thy viſitations with faith: help vs in the time of this wea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſſe, and danger of this diſeaſe; if thou giue life, graunt amendment of life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>If thou appoint death, grant vs preparation for our diſſolution; Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for our ſinnes, and a ioyfull aſſurance of thy mercies: the bodie is weake, the fleſh trem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les, the Spirit is troubled. O thou the giuer of life, and the diſpoſer of death, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſenſe is dull or diſtracted,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:455:51"/> infuſe thy Spirit to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per it, and to turne vs vnto thee: diſpoſe our harts ſo, that whither life or death do come, they may bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like welcome vnto vs, and we may entertaine either, according to thy good wil and pleaſure. Arme vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the feare of death: if life be graunted, graunt wee may leade a new life, ſetting forth thy glory.</p>
            <p>If death be deſigned, let the period of this life bee finiſhed in thy praiſes, lift vp our hearts at the laſt gaſpe. And now at this inſtant, plant in my heart faith to beleeue in thy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing health, feruencie to pray for it, courage to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the conflicts of ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and of ſinne, and in
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:455:51"/> the end a bleſſed death, and a ioyfull reſurrection, thorow Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="knowledge" type="prayer">
            <head>A prayer for knowledge.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou (O great and gracious God,) who art the light of our liues, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruer of all ſauing know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, enlighten our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding with the true knowledge of thee, of our ſelues, and of the wayes wherein we ſhould walke. And although we can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in this world knowe thee as thou art, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible, &amp; infinit in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and in greatnes; yet giue vs ſuch, and ſo much
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:455:52"/> knowledge of thee, as our capacities can compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, and thy will is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueale. Let vs attaine to ſo much knowledge, as to ſee thy wonders in thy works and thy good pleaſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed in thy word: if that which thou haſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed of thy ſelfe, let vs bee ſatisfied with what thou haſt reuealed in thy word.</p>
            <p>Of the firſt, let our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall inquiſition of thy ſupernaturall power, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or preiudice our faith: And in that knowledge which thy word deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, let vs not be content with a weake and meane meaſure, but couet to come vnto that knowledg which may ſtrengthen our
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:455:52"/> faith, informe our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and reforme our liues. In the knowledge of our ſelues, teach vs to conſider and know our owne weakneſſe and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, our frailtie and manifold infirmities, our ſinnes and tranſgreſſions againſt thy holy and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Maieſty.</p>
            <p>For the knowledge of our owne wayes, grant vs warineſſe and watchfulnes to ſee and finde out our faylings in the keeping of thy Commandements: our feare, plainly to profeſſe thy truth, thorow doubt of danger, ſcoffe, or loſſe: the ſmal account we make of thy good things wee leaue vndone, or do amis, of the euill wee haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted:
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:455:53"/> And when (good Lord) thou haſt rightly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed vs in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of thee, by thy works and word; of our ſelues, in finding and confeſſing our ſinnes: and of our owne wayes, by acknowledging them to be wandering by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paths; then bring vs home vnto thee, to pray vnto thee, and praiſe thee in this life, and in the life to come, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="lusts" type="prayer">
            <head>A prayer to be kept from all vncleanneſſe of our Luſtes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Moſt eternall and gracious GOD, thou art pure and perfect; but we are moſt impure and polluted: all
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:455:53"/> the faculties of our ſoules are full of corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and our bodyes are fraught with infirmities: thoſe parts of our bodies and of our mindes, which ſhould be the ſeruants of our ſoules, doe draw vs to be ſlaues to euil affections: Our eyes which are ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to behold &amp; contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plate the wonderful work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip of the world, and of all the creatures there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained, do common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly become like vnto ſluces and flood-gates, to carrie and conuey luſt and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence vnto our harts; and our harts which ſhold be as Cloſſets to keep thy Commandements, are for the moſt part, made the members and inſtruments
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:455:54"/> of ſinne and of Satan. This (O Lord) we confeſſe is our wofull and wretched condition.</p>
            <p>Yet thou (O moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull God) art able to cleanſe vs from theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagions of our vncleane luſts, purge vs (we beſeech thee) and we ſhall be pure: keepe vs from inward in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of our owne euill imaginations, &amp; from out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward temptations, which laſciuious ſights and dalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and fleſhly prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations pull vpon vs, and that by the aſſiſtance of thy holy Spirite, when theſe temptations aſſalt vs, pray vnto thee, beſeeching thee to be our buckler and our ſtrength in the time of our weakneſſe; our ſtay when
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:455:54"/> we are ready to fall, and that by thy power wee may reſiſt and repel all the ſenſuall and fleſhly luſtes which are in vs, and fight againſt vs. Wee haue no helpe, nor no hope but in thee: defend vs, giue vs the victory, and take the glory vnto thy ſelfe: deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs from theſe noyſome luſts, and giue vs grace to giue thee praiſe, to whom all honor belongeth. So be it good Lord, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="before sermon" type="prayer">
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:455:55"/>
            <head>A Prayer before the hearing of the Word preached.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hy Word (O Lord) is a light vnto our feete, and a Lanterne vnto our paths. Thy word preached is the propagati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy glorious Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, it is the ſeed that fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifies knowledge &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Let it not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be as good ſeede ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen in barren ſoyle; but firſt clenſe the weedes and corruptions which growe in the vnfallowed fields of my heart. And then (moſt gracious God) when thou haſt remoued thoſe impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments of faith and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uency:
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:455:55"/> make my heart by hearing thy holy word, a harbour of ſanctitie and ſincerity. And in this (O Lord) prepare me to hear, to beleeue, to receyue, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and to remember the leſſons that ſhall bee taught out of thy Sacred Word; take away in the hearing thereof, all drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, diſtraction, and coldneſſe of zeale.</p>
            <p>In this I pray not onely for my ſelfe, but for the people in all places profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thy trueth, for their profit, and for thy glorie. Send forth Labourers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy Vineyard, teach them to plant: make vs to be plyant in hearing, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and following. So ſhall wee haue ſuſtenance
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:455:56"/> vnto our ſoules; reape the fruites of thoſe fields that thou haſt giuen vs: and we ſhall giue vnto thee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what is thine, and belongs to thy Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, which is all honour, glory, praiſe, and domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thorow Ieſus Chriſt our onely Lord &amp; Sauiour, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="after sermon" type="prayer">
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:455:56"/>
            <head>A Prayer after the hearing of a Sermon.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST mercifull and mighty go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerner of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen &amp; of earth, amongſt all thy bleſſings multiplied vpon mankind, there is nothing doeth more magnifie thy Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, or helpe the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of vs miſerable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, then the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our weakenes and wickedneſſe, in the reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of both, and reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation of thy ſelfe (after all our infinite tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions) thorow the ſuffering of thy Sonne, his mediati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the Miniſterie of the word preached. Of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:455:57"/> this (O Lord) we haue bin vnprofitable hearers and learners. We haue heard with our eares, but yet we haue beene vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hearers. We haue not felt and followed that we haue heard: we haue bene told, and plainely taught our ſinnes, but wee haue not amended them, nor truly repented for our miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeds. We haue learned ſomewhat, though but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; haue performed and practiſed leſſe, the fault is ours: yet let it not (good Lord) ſtand in the way of thy grace, to ſtop from vs good things: but as thou haſt prouided for vs the word of life, and haſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueied it by thy conducter, men like our ſelues, the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:455:57"/> Miniſters and Preachers of thy Goſpell; ſo graunt that we go not from this exerciſe of preaching and publiſhing thy holy word, like vnto empty veſſelles, which whilſt they are moued and ſtrucken vpon yeeld ſome ſound; but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards lying ſtill, afford neyther ſweetnes, ſauour, nor good liquor. O Lord bleſſe &amp; fructifie our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, make vs not onely hearers, but dooers of thy word: make it a ſauour of life vnto life, and not of death vnto death: teach vs thereby to amend our liues, to increaſe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and conſcience, to yeelde comfort in afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſtrength and ſupport in temptations, and when
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:455:58"/> we ſhall depart the world, we may carry with vs a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, that we haue profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the word, haue thereby learned to loue our Brethren, to forſake ſinne, to imbrace righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, to liue and to die well, and that by faith in Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="before Communion" type="prayer">
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:455:58"/>
            <head>A Prayer before the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the Lords Supper.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Leſſed Lord, wee do not preſume to preſent our ſelues before thee, in the recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of this Sacrament, &amp; celebration of thy Sonnes laſt Supper, as beleeuing we are of our ſelues wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be partakers of thy heauenly banquet. For we acknowledge our great &amp; greeuous ſinnes, our mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold miſtakings, our vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe, vncharitableneſſe, hardneſſe of heart, ſelfe-loue, pride, and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with many other tranſgreſſions, wherby we are made moſt vnworthie
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:455:59"/> to come vnto thy heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Table. Yet, O Lord, as it is thy holy Ordinance, inſtruct and help vs to do that which may make vs more meete partakers of this ſpirituall Manna. To this end, take from vs our corruptions and careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in thy ſeruice: graunt vs true repentance for our ſinnes paſt, for the treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that we haue commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt thee and thoſe that profeſſe thy trueth. Lord, euen now giue mee thy vnworthy ſeruant (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo vnable of my ſelfe to doe this, or any other ſpirituall duty) a right and regenerated heart, a ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified ſoule, purged from former pollutions, by thy power, and the grace of
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:455:59"/> thy holy Spirite; a deſire to forgiue all men, and to be forgiuen of all men, to forſake ſinne, to follow thy holy Lawes. Suffer not Sathan to worke in me his will any more, but that as I now come to receyue this Sacrament, ſo I may be a partaker of the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites of our Sauiours death and ſuffering, wherof this is a ſymbole: that thorow his death ſinne may dye in me, and thorow his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, I may riſe to newneſſe of life.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="after Communion" type="prayer">
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:455:60"/>
            <head>A Prayer after the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE bleſſe and praiſe thy holie name (O hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father) that amongſt all thy innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable benefits thou haſt beſtowed, this is not the leaſt but greateſt mercie vppon mankinde, to ſend thy Sonne our Sauiour into the world to ſuffer for vs ſinners, to redeeme vs from life to death, to lay downe his owne life to ſaue vs from damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This thy mercie, as it is vnſpeakeable and vnua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lewable, O Lord wee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:455:60"/> it to bee ſo great, that we cannot giue thee condigne prayſes, but doe pray thee to accept our weake ſacrifices in the Euchariſticall reioycing &amp; rendering of laud vnto thee, for the ſuffering of thy Sonne, to offer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto death, euen for them that were become enemies to our gracious God, breakers of thy Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenants, defilers of thy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths, haters of truth, truce breakers, loaden with ſin, and voyde of grace.</p>
            <p>Now moſt mercifull Lord God, that thou haſt vouchſafed vs this fauour to approach vnto thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Table, and to renew the ſeale of the Couenant; graunt likewiſe for a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:455:61"/> addition of grace, &amp; for the increaſe of thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, that we may approach neerer and neerer vnto thee, by newneſſe of life, watchfulneſſe ouer our owne wayes, firmeneſſe in faith, conſtancie in kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thy Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, obedience to thy holy word and will, and this thorow the helpe of thee our Lord, which on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly art able to ſaue thoſe that ſerue thee, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="weather" type="prayer">
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:455:61"/>
            <head>A prayer in the time of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He heauens, the earth, and all the Creatures therein contained, thou (O Lord) haſt ordained: thou in thy eternall counſell and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, haſt appoynted ſeaſons of the yeere fit to produce and propagate things needfull for the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenance and vſe of man, and haſt vſually ſent wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fit for thoſe ſeaſons: but our ſinnes, which one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make a ſeperation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt thee and vs, haue cauſed ſome alterations of theſe ſeaſons, &amp; hath ſent
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:455:62"/> many times vnſeaſonable weather, wherby the fruits of the earth haue not come to their full ripenes, the Cattle haue not theyr nouriſhment, and man by this meanes wants things neceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry. All this, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy chaſtiſements, we confeſſe do come from the demerits of our owne ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full liues, which draw on deſeruedly, thy iuſt indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>Yet (O Lord) ſince on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thy mercie can free vs from miſeries, firſt free vs from our ſinnes the cauſes of them, and then from the puniſhment they haue procured. Make our harts cleane, ſo make the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeaſonable, vs mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in the vſe of thy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:455:62"/> them holſome to vs, and with the amendment of the weather amend our liues, and forgiue our ſins. So chaunge vs, that thy chaſtiſement may be taken away, and by this let vs learne to conſider thy po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, to confeſſe thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and to ſet foorth thy praiſe, throughout all ages, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="famine" type="prayer">
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:455:63"/>
            <head>A Prayer to be vſed vvhen dearth and ſcarſity comes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Moſt gracious Lord God, thou which diddeſt permit <hi>Ioſephs</hi> Brethren to ſell, &amp; to ſend him into Egypt, that hee being carried from his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into a ſtrange Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, might there in time of moſt want and neceſſitie, after the ouer-paſſing of his owne afflictions, be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make prouiſion, not onely for his Fathers Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, but alſo for his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, from which hee was carried: So wee (good Lord) being ſolde by our
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:455:63"/> owne ſelues vnto ſinne &amp; Sathan, thereby carried in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Egypt of Ignorance and Iniquitie, doe beſeech thee by thine owne mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, to grant vs true repen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tance, that the ſcarſity thou haſt ſent, may bee remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Encreaſe our Faith, zeale, ſorrow for our ſins, with amendment of life; and therewith encreaſe our ſtore, the fruits of the earth, and prouiſion of the Land, that hauing ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie, wee may therewith haue content, and thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.</p>
            <p>Comfort vs in thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and conſolations in the continuance of thy loue. Let vs not (O Lord) with the prodigall Sonne, miſpend our times, eſtates,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:455:64"/> and thy bleſſings, but with the penitent Publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can, lift vp our hearts and hands vnto Heauen, &amp; ſay ſtill from the heart, <hi>God be mercifull vnto vs miſerable ſinners.</hi> So good Lord, take away this dearth, and our ſinnes, which will bring vs vnto death.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="plague" type="prayer">
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:455:64"/>
            <head>A Prayer in time of plague and peſtilence.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Contagion and corruption of our bodies comming (O Lord) from the ſinnes of our ſoules, brings all the diſeaſes of our bodies, and dangers of our liues. So are we filled with infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which threatneth death vnto vs, when as we ſee others dayly die before our eyes. Since then (good Lord) thou giueſt vs a ſight, and continual repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of our mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, giue vs alſo a ſenſe and a true feeling, with a tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row repentance of all our
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:455:65"/> ſinnes paſt, the cauſers of all our woe, diſtreſſe, and perill: and as our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent by his fall, and our naturall parents by theyr tranſgreſſions, haue drawn vppon themſelues and vs, death and deſtruction, and we our ſelues by our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall iniquities, haue added more curſes to our parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons, and to the publike ſtate wherein wee liue: ſo yet (good Lord) remember thy Couenant of Grace; remember the Sonne of thy loue, and his ſufferings, whom thou haſt ſent into the world, for the redemption of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde: let theſe thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and long continued mercies, mooue thee to continue thy compaſſion,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:455:65"/> in remoouing thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from vs, in renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the graces of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Spirit, in teaching vs to repent, and renounce our former euill liues.</p>
            <p>Then let thy Angel and Meſſenger of good ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, our Mediator, ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle the poſtes and doores of our hearts, with the blood of that Paſchall Lambe, who hath ſhedde his blood for the ſinnes of the world in ſuch ſort, that receiuing grace from thy all-giuing grace, our ſins and puniſhments for the ſame may ceaſe, and wee may with purified hearts after all our pollutions, learn to publiſh thy praiſe; and hauing receyued de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance for the contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:455:66"/> of ſoule and of bodie, may be made inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of thy glory, both in this world, and in the world to come.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="graces" type="prayer">
            <pb n="119" facs="tcp:455:66"/>
            <head>A Prayer for increaſe and continuance of ſpirituall giftes and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Almighty God; though wee are weake, and not ſtrong of our ſelues, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the ſpirituall graces which might make vs beu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull corner-ſtones in thy Celeſtiall building, yet thou (good Lord) who haſt created Heauen and Earth, and doeſt conſerue all heerein contayned, art able by thy wonderfull Workemanſhip, not onely to begin, and to beget, but to increaſe and to preſerue in our hearts the ſeedes of
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:455:67"/> humility, penitence, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, piety, zeale, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good ſauing Graces. We are thy creatures, and thou our Creator: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though we haue long dwelt in darkeneſſe, yet now ſend vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light of thy countenance, to enlighten our vnderſtanding: the ſeale and teſtimony of thy holy Spirit, to aſſure our hearts and conſciences of thy loue, and of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>To this end, giue vs for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and corage to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thy cauſe, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the trueth; a ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power to maſter our owne luſtes, and to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due our ſinnes; wiſedome from aboue, to withſtand the aſſaults of Sathan; ſo
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:455:67"/> of Captiues made Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors, and of ſlaues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſinne and ſathan, made ſubduers of them both. We may by the ſame thy mercy and power, magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thy Maieſty, hallow thy name, not only in this world, but in the world to come, thorow all Ages, euen euerlaſtingly. So be it, and ſo cauſe it to be done good Lord, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="preparation for death" type="prayer">
            <pb n="124" facs="tcp:455:68"/>
            <head>A Prayer to bee prepared for death.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr liues good Lord) we ſee are ſhort, and moſt vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, our ſouls are full of ſinne, our ſelues are ſubiect to many dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, wee couet poſſeſſions and preferments, but know not how long wee ſhall enioy them, nor are wee aſſured who ſhall haue them, when we leaue this life. Moſt mercifull God, teach vs ſo to meditate, and ſo to meaſure this ſpanne, and ſhort ſpace of fading life, that finding how fraile it is, wee may

<pb n="125" facs="tcp:455:68"/> paſſe this our pilgrimage, in a conſcionable courſe; not miſpending time in vaine or vicious liuing, waiting for the time of our diſſolution, awaking our ſpirits from ſin and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, wherein we haue laien as in a ſlumber, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on to death. Good God giue vs faith in the blood of thy Son, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance for our former euill wayes, reconciliation by thy mercies, and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of our Redeemer. Shut vp our exterior ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from thoſe obiects of ſinne, which betraid our ſoules; ſettle our interiour ſences to repoſe: freed by thy fauours, from Paſſion, Anger, Ambition, Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence, Couetouſneſſe,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:455:69"/> Luſt, Vncharitableneſſe, Vnbeleefe, and all other wickedneſſe which defile and deſtroy our ſoules; ſo being purged from our polutions, and being guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and guided by thy good gouerning Spirite, wee may make this life a meditation of death; the time to come, a cure of former treſpaſſes; and the concluſion of all, to be thy glory, the good of thy Church, the maintenance of thy trueth, &amp; finally the ſaluation of our ſoules, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="near death" type="prayer">
            <pb n="127" facs="tcp:455:69"/>
            <head>A prayer to be vſed when death drawes neere.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> LORD, this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and vncertaine life, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> I haue led, being now drawne neere amend, I beſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch thee, that haſt hitherto prolonged life, and now doeſt diſpoſe death, purge me from my ſinnes paſt, by the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blood, and powerfull death of thy Son our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt Ieſus, in his wounds, and by his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings waſh away our ſins. In this ſhort ſeaſon of my time almoſt all ſpent, grant me hearty repentance, for my tranſgreſſions a lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging deſire of a better life,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:455:70"/> a change not onely from my corruptions, but from all my former failings; and as natural ſtrength growes weaker, ſo grant that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Graces in mee may grow ſtronger.</p>
            <p>Helpe Lord to quicken my ſinfull ſences, to quiet my conſcience with aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of thy fauour and mercy. Be with mee, by thy all-aſſiſting aide, as in my life ſo at my death; that neither ſinne, death, nor hell may haue the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt ouer mee, but ſo ſtrengthned &amp; ſaued: com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending my ſpirite and ſoule vnto thy ſafeguard, thou that haſt made it, will vouchſafe to ſaue it: for thy Sonne, and for thy owne mercies ſake. I come
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:455:70"/> Lord, come thou vnto me. I faint; Lord ſtrengthen me. My life departs, yet ſaue my ſinfull ſoule. Lord I come, helpe me to come vnto thee. Lift vp mine eyes, my hands, my heart, Lord receiue and ſaue my ſoule.</p>
            <p>Let this laſt ſentence be often ſaid as long as ſpeech doth laſt; and bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly conceiued when words can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:455:71"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:455:71"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>A</hi> Prayer for deuotion in prayer. <hi>58</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Morning prayer in a Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>61</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A morning prayer to be vſed in priuate. <hi>66</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for the Euening in the Family. <hi>68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A priuate prayer for one go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to bed. <hi>73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Certaine Meditations, and ſhort eiaculations of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to bee vſed in the night.
<hi>75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A praier for deliuerance from temptations. <hi>77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for patience in
<pb facs="tcp:455:72"/> time of wants and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.
<hi>80</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer in time of ſicknes. <hi>83</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer for knowledge. <hi>89</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer to bee kept from all vncleanneſſe of our luſtes. <hi>92</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer before the hearing of the word preached. <hi>96</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer after the hearing of a Sermon. <hi>99</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer before the recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the Lords Supper. <hi>103</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer after the receiuing of the holy Communion. <hi>106</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer in the time of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable weather. <hi>109</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer to be vſed vvhen dearth &amp; ſcarſity comes. <hi>112</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer in time of plague
<pb facs="tcp:455:72"/> and peſtilence. <hi>115</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Prayer for increaſe and continuance of ſpirituall giftes and graces.
<hi>119</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer to bee prepared for death. <hi>124</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer to bee ſaide when death drawes neere. <hi>127</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
